{"tossups": [{"question": "This war included the first U.S. use of the terms \"D-day\" and \"H-hour\" in military combat at Saint-Mihiel [[SANH-mee-HYEL]]. Omar Bundy helped lead men in this war at a battle at which Lloyd Williams quipped, \"Retreat? Hell, we just got here.\" The pigeon Cher Ami [[SHEHR ah-MEE]] helped save the Lost Battalion in this war during the Battle of the Argonne Forest. The idea of the Devil Dog came from this war's Battle of Belleau Wood. The Harlem Hellfighters fought in, for ten points, what \"war to end all wars\"?", "answer": "<b><u>World</u></b> War <b><u>One</u></b> (or <b><u>First World</u></b> War; accept the <b><u>Great</u></b> War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An 1802 James Gilray cartoon protesting the use of these things depicted the \"Cow Pock,\" with cows emerging from people's bodies. The first one of these things was made using sores that appeared on the hands of milkmaids. Recent examples of these things utilize mRNA to program cells to produce a certain \"spike protein.\" Jonas Salk is best known for developing an inactivated one of these things to fight polio. For ten points, name these things which are typically injected to prevent a patient from contracting a disease.", "answer": "<b><u>Vaccine</u></b> (accept <b><u>Inoculation</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "Ferdinand Lot questioned whether this man actually defeated 430 thousand enemy soldiers, though Ernest Desjardins [[day-zhar-DAH]] credited that number to a transcription error. Aulus Hirtius [[OW-luss HEAR-shus]] wrote the eighth book of one of this man's works which features Vorenus and Pullo. A work by this man describes his defeat of Vercingetorix [[VEHR-sin-GET-or-rix]], and this man wrote <em>Commentaries on the Gallic</em> <em>Wars</em>. Known for crossing the Rubicon, for ten points, who was this Roman who was killed on the Ides of March?", "answer": "Gaius <b><u>Julius</u></b> Caesar (prompt on \"Caesar\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Herman Melville's novel <em>The Confidence-Man</em> depicts travelers telling stories along this body of water. In one novel, a pair of con artists traveling on this body of water pretend to be King Louis XVII and the Duke of Nonesuch [[NUN-such]]. A memoir titled <em>Life on</em> [this body of water] was written by Mark Twain, who set many of his novels along this waterway.  For ten points, name this long U.S. river, on which Jim and Huckleberry Finn float in a raft.", "answer": "<b><u>Mississippi</u></b> River", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "The annexation of what is now this state was facilitated under the Newlands Resolution during the William McKinley administration. This state was formerly a Republic which was led by Sanford Dole. Sugarcane planters overthrew this modern day state\u2019s native ruler, Queen Lili\u02bbuokalani [[lee-lee-woh-kah-LUH-nee]]. For ten points, name this state in which an attack on a base which included Battleship Row served as a precursor to U.S. entry into World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Hawai'i</u></b> (accept Kingdom of <b><u>Hawai'i</u></b>; accept Republic of <b><u>Hawai'i</u></b>; accept Territory of <b><u>Hawai'i</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The creator of this game series founded MicroProse in 1982, which produced products such as an historically-based game which allowed players to sail the Spanish Main as a pirate. In the 2016 release from this series, players can reveal the Hermetic Order secret society by discovering a natural wonder. That game in this series also includes a civics tree to parallel its technology tree and features novel playable factions such as the Scythians and the Hungarians. For ten points, name this strategic computer game series whose entries bear the name of creator Sid Meier.", "answer": "<em>Sid Meier's</em> <em><b><u>Civilization</u></b></em> (accept <em>Sid Meier\u2019s</em> <em><b><u>Civilization</u></b></em> VI)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This region was home to three confederacies, together known as the Samhan, who fought against Qin Kai [[CHIN KAI]] and the Yan. Wei Man invaded this region to end a dynasty supposedly founded by Dangun and a mythical bear-woman. Four Han Commanderies, including Leland and Lintun, were set up after this region's state of Gojoseon [[GOH-joh-sun]] was captured. This region's three kingdoms were Baekje [[BECK-jeh]], Goguryeo [[GOH-guhr-yuh]], and Silla. For ten points, name this peninsula which today includes a country led by Kim Jong Un.", "answer": "<b><u>Korea</u></b>n Peninsula", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was born in what is today Algeria and wrote one of the first autobiographies in Western literature in which he relates his sinful early life and the tireless efforts of his mother, Monica, to save his soul. As a young man in Carthage, this future theologian was enamored of Manichaeism [[man-ih-KEE-ism]], the belief in an eternal conflict between light and darkness. In Milan, this man met Saint Ambrose, who eventually baptized him into the Catholic church. For ten points, what saint and Bishop of Hippo wrote the <em>Confessions</em>?", "answer": "Saint <b><u>Augustine</u></b> of Hippo", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Two answers required. A coalition led by these two cities lost to the <em>strategos</em> Epaminondas [[ee-pam-ih-NON-dahs]] at the Battle of Mantinea under the leadership of a king of the Eurypontid dynasty. One of these cities tore down the other\u2019s \u201cLong Wall\u201d which reached Piraeus [[pie-RAY-us]], and these two states signed the \"fifty year\" Peace of Nicias. Admiral Lysander from one of these cities sank the other city\u2019s Delian fleet during the Battle of Aegospotami [[ay-goh-SPOH-tah-mai]]. For ten points, name these two Greek <em>poleis</em> [[POH-lice]] which fought each other in the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b><u>Athens</u></b> and <b><u>Sparta</u></b> (accept in either order)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In this state, market manipulation and megawatt laundering by traders under false names like \u201cDeath Star\u201d and \u201cRed Congo\u201d led to rolling blackouts during the late 1990s and early 2000s. The murder of 15-year old Latasha Harlins by Soon Ja Du was one of the factors that increased racial tensions and led to the 1992 riots in this state. The successful recall of this state\u2019s governor, Gray Davis, in 2003 led to the eventual election of actor Arnold Schwarzenegger. For ten points, name this state with the cities of Sacramento and Los Angeles.", "answer": "<b><u>California</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Rupert of Wittelsbach [[VITT-els-BACH]], \"the Gentle\", was bankrolled by this city, whose aristocrats were targeted by its Ordinances of Justice. Bankers from this city were ruined when Edward III refused to pay his debts. \"The 8 Saints\" supported guildless artisans in this city's Ciompi [[CHOM-pee]] Revolt. This city became a republic after it rebelled following the death of Matilda of Tuscany. Housing art galleries such as the Uffizi, for ten points, name this major Italian city once led by the Medici family.", "answer": "<b><u>Florence</u></b> (Accept <b><u>Firenze</u></b> or <b><u>Fiorentino</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Abram Joseph Ryan was considered the \"Poet-Priest\" of one side of this war for poems like \"The Conquered Banner.\" Allen Tate wrote a modernist poem as an \u201cOde\u201d to this war\u2019s dead, told by a narrator in a graveyard on an \"Ambitious November.\u201d Ambrose Bierce\u2019s experiences during this war inspired his short story \u201cChickamauga.\u201d Jim Conklin dies from blood loss in an engagement in this war, causing Henry Fleming to flee the battlefield. For ten points, name this war depicted in <em>The Red Badge of Courage</em>.", "answer": "American <b><u>Civil War</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "Albert Toven and Randy Lawrence discovered aluminum versions of these objects which had been released in 1974, but were told they were government property. A large version of these objects included Wreath, Flowing Hair, and Draped Bust variants. Victor Brenner designed the Wheat stalk variety of these objects, many of which depict Abraham Lincoln. Made of zinc and copper, it is debated whether these coins are still necessary. For ten points, name this smallest denomination of U.S. coinage.", "answer": "U.S. <b><u>Penny</u></b> (accept <b><u>One-Cent</u></b> piece)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Several iterations of this entity were criticized for being political statements against the Bush Administration. A member of the Swedish parliament nominated Adolf Hitler for one of these in 1939. In 2010, a Chinese group created a competitor to this prize named for Confucius as a response to one of these being given to Liu Xiaobo [[LOO SHAO-BOH]]. First given to Henri Dunant [[doo-NANH]] and Fr\u00e9d\u00e9ric Passy in 1901, for ten points, what is this award, one of five established in the will of a Swedish industrialist?", "answer": "<b><u>Nobel Peace</u></b> Prize (prompt on <b><u>Nobel</u></b> Prize)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One work dictated by this man was partially lost by his neighbor, Martin Harris, and was allegedly verified in the presence of the Three Witnesses. Religious communities established by this man included those in Kirtland and Independence. This man was murdered by a mob after he ordered the destruction of a printing press for the <em>Expositor</em>. This man claimed to have been given two golden plates containing sacred texts by the angel Moroni. For ten points, name this founder of the Mormon Church.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Smith</u></b>, Jr.", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "Confederate sympathizers from this nation led by Vernon Guyon Locke captured and commandeered a Union steamer in the Chesapeake Affair. Rebels from this nation entered U.S. waters while aboard the <em>Caroline</em>, which was later burned by British forces. The death of General Richard Montgomery occurred during an invasion of this nation, leading to Benedict Arnold taking over and heading an ineffectual siege of Quebec City. For ten points, name this northern neighbor of the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Canada</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Defenders secret society operated on this island, losing the Battle of the Diamond. The Battle of Vinegar Hill took place near Wexford during a French-supported rebellion on this island led by Wolfe Tone. This island's lands were concentrated in Protestant hands in the Ascendency. Charles Parnell led a home-rule movement on this island, whose oldest surviving university is Trinity College. For ten points, what island contains a Republic with its capital at Dublin?", "answer": "<b><u>Ireland</u></b> (accept <b><u>Eire</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Antonio Gramsci referred to this philosophy as the \"philosophy of praxis\" in his <em>Prison Notebooks</em> while imprisoned by Italy's Fascist regime. With Arnold Ruge [[ROO-guh]], this philosophy's namesake led the newspaper the <em>German-French Annals</em>. Lesser known books by this philosophy's namesake include <em>Grundrisse</em> and <em>The German Ideology</em>. Espoused by the Maoist and Bolshevik parties, for ten points, what is this communist philosophy named after the author of <em>Das Kapital</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Marxism</u></b> (prompt on \"communism\" before mentioned; prompt on \"socialism\")  This Marxist philosopher outlined his namesake philosophy in books such as <em>The</em> <em>State and Revolution</em> and <em>Imperialism: the Highest Stage of Capitalism</em>. This revolutionary also issued ten directives in his \"April Theses.\"  ANSWER: Vladimir Ilyich <b><u>Lenin</u></b> (accept Vladimire Ilyich <b><u>Ulyanov</u></b>)  <b> </b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's government laid out the human research principles of \"respect</u></b> <b><u>for persons, beneficence, and justice\" in the Belmont Report. Researchers from this</u></b> <b><u>country took the HeLa [[HEE-LAH]] cell line from a woman from this country without</u></b> <b><u>her consent. From 1932 to 1972, researchers in this nation allowed impoverished (+)</u></b> <b>Black men to go untreated from syphilis. This country's intelligence agency carried out mind control experiments as part of Project (*) </b>MK-Ultra. For ten points, name this country in which the unethical Tuskegee Studies were carried out in Alabama.", "answer": "<b><u>United States</u></b> of America (or <b><u>US</u></b>A; accept <b><u>America</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A ruler of this empire named Alexander died of exhaustion after playing</u></b> <em><b><u>tzykanisterion</u></b></em><b><u> [[tzik-an-ih-STEER-ee-on]], a form of polo. This empire was defended</u></b> <b><u>by strongholds called</u> </b><em><b><u>al-thughur</u></b></em><b><u> [[al THOO-goor]] between it and the (+)</u> Umayyads and Abbasids. This empire faced Leo of Tripoli's sack while \"Oleg the Prophet\" attacked its capital, leading to a 911 treaty with the Rus. (*) </b>Leo VI the Wise and Basil the Bulgar-Slayer ruled, for ten points, what empire from Constantinople?", "answer": "<b><u>Byzantine</u></b> Empire (accept <b><u>Byzantine</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Eastern Roman</u></b> Empire; do not accept or prompt on \"Roman Empire\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One band from this country helped popularize distortion in rock music when</u></b> <b><u>they sliced their amp with a razor to record the song \"You Really Got Me.\" While</u></b> <b><u>performing in Des Moines, Iowa, one musician from this country (+)</u> bit off the head of a dead bat. Another musician from this country was assassinated by Mark David Chapman. Bands from this country such as The Kinks were part of a 1960s (*) </b>\"Invasion\" from this country to the United States. For ten points, name this country, home to rock bands such as Black Sabbath, The Rolling Stones, and the Beatles.", "answer": "<b><u>United Kingdom</u></b> (or <b><u>UK</u></b>; accept Great <b><u>Britain</u></b>; accept <b><u>England</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>A classic image of this figure may have been modeled on a photo of Naomi</u></b> <b><u>Parker which has been misattributed as Geraldine Hoff. J. Howard Miller was hired to</u></b> <b><u>create that image of this figure for (+)</u> Westinghouse Electric. Based on actual people working in historically male-dominated jobs, much like \"Wendy the Welder,\" this figure was depicted wearing a (*) </b>red bandana and flexing her arm in a poster which read \"We Can Do It!\" Norman Rockwell popularized, for ten points, what female icon, modeled on real factory workers during World War Two?", "answer": "<b><u>Rosie the Riveter</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Isamu Nogachi's sculpture</u> </b><em><b><u>Floor Frame</u></b></em><b><u> is displayed in this building's garden,</u></b> <b><u>making him the first artist of Asian lineage to be exhibited here. Childe Hassam's</u></b> <b><u>painting</u> </b><em><b><u>The Avenue in the Rain</u></b></em><b><u> is displayed in this building. James McNeill Whistler</u></b> <b><u>and Thomas Jeckyll collaborated on the (+)</u> Peacock Room in this building. An enslaved person rescued the Lansdowne portrait from this building during the (*) </b>War of 1812. For ten points, name this building in Washington, D.C., whose decoration has historically been overseen by the First Lady.", "answer": "<b><u>White House</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>States surrounding this one were called Limitrophe [[LEE-meh-trohf]] states</u></b> <b><u>which formed the cordon sanitaire [[kor-DONH sahn-ee-TEHR]]. Territorial parts of</u></b> <b><u>this country underwent \"korenization.\" Winston Churchill (+)</u> handed over political control of satellite states to this country in his Mediterranean Strategy, via the Percentages Agreement which left Greece to the Western allies while forsaking (*) </b>Bulgaria and Romania to communism. For ten points, name this country which was led by Josef Stalin.", "answer": "<b><u>U</u></b>nion of <b><u>S</u></b>oviet <b><u>S</u></b>ocialist <b><u>R</u></b>epublics (accept <b><u>Soviet Union</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Russia\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man led a battalion in a desperate attempt to break Gordon Drummond\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>line during the 1814 Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane, where this man's leadership showed that</u></b> <b><u>the U.S. had a truly professional army. This general had his orders disobeyed by</u></b> <b><u>future (+)</u> electoral opponent Franklin Pierce during the Battle of Churubusco [[choo-roo-BOO-skoh]]. This general captured both (*) </b>Veracruz and Mexico City during the Mexican-American War and was nicknamed \"Old Fuss n' Feathers.\" For ten points, name this 1852 Whig presidential candidate, a general who formulated the Anaconda Plan.", "answer": "Winfield <b><u>Scott</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>British forces captured Mahmoud Fehmy in this country and attacked their</u></b> <b><u>opponents at Kassassin. Prince Arthur, the son of Queen Victoria, led a bayonet</u></b> <b><u>charge under Garnet Wolseley's command in this country for which William Marsh</u></b> <b><u>Edwards won a Victoria Cross. This country, the site of the Battle of (+)</u> Tel El Kebir, was the location of Richard Eve's defense of Ahmed 'Urabi. In 1919, Saad Zaghlul led this country's Wafd party to rebel. Once governed by (*) </b>Muhammad Ali, for ten points, what is this country, considered geographically to be in both Africa and Asia?", "answer": "Arab Republic of <b><u>Egypt</u></b> (accept Khedivate of <b><u>Egypt</u></b>; accept Sultanate of <b><u>Egypt</u></b>; accept Ottoman <b><u>Egypt</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The 1688 Bill of Rights was breached by a politician from this country, as</u></b> <b><u>heard in the</u> </b><em><b><u>Fitzgerald</u></b></em><b><u> case. A National party prime minister of this country used</u></b> <b><u>Think Big industrial projects and led the \"government of the ordinary bloke\" before</u></b> <b><u>David (+)</u> Lange succeeded him. In 1984, a leader from this country drunkenly called for a snap vote and was defeated in the \"Schnapps election.\" Maintaining \"Closer Economic Relations\" with (*) </b>Australia, for ten points, what is this country which Robert Muldoon governed from Wellington?", "answer": "<b><u>New Zealand</u></b> (or <b><u>Aotearoa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}